<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Culture on Mark Barta</title><link>https://bartamark.com/tags/culture/</link><description>Mark Barta (Culture)</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://bartamark.com/tags/culture/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Why collaboration and healthy conflict shouldn't be part of your culture.</title><link>https://bartamark.com/post/healthyconflictredflag/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bartamark.com/post/healthyconflictredflag/</guid><description>&lt;p>Clickbait aside - Because they&amp;rsquo;re not specific. How we communicate is important, but how we communicate our culture is critical. There is some wiggle room in large organizations to give room for sub cultures, but even then, we can give more guidance with the words we choose.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Think of Facebook&amp;rsquo;s famous line - &amp;ldquo;Move fast and break things&amp;rdquo;. This tells us how to make decisions and where to focus - and more. Lets compare that with &amp;ldquo;We are a team of disruptors&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s energizing, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t offer a way to disrupt.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Collaboration&amp;rdquo; is the biggest offender with it meaning so many things. I remember working at one place where some teams used Slack and others used Email. Any type of collaboration meant having the same conversation twice - once in Slack and once in Email. Were we collaborating? Technically, but if our own tools and processes couldn&amp;rsquo;t work together, it didn&amp;rsquo;t seem in good faith.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Healthy Conflict&amp;rdquo; poses a similar problem. You may actually mean &amp;ldquo;honest and open communication&amp;rdquo;. Or you want to &amp;ldquo;challenge the status quo&amp;rdquo;. But &amp;ldquo;healthy conflict&amp;rdquo; introduces the risk of misinterpretation where conflict is OK. The last thing you want are bad actors leveraging your values as a defense.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Assume the ambiguous, State the specific&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Take it to the next step - how do you want teams to collaborate? Imagine the perfect culture and describe what they&amp;rsquo;re doing. Is there pair programming? Instead of &amp;ldquo;Collaborate&amp;rdquo;, say &amp;ldquo;Build Together&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Mentorship&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Being specific also plays into setting expectations. If you want people to live up to your values, you need to define what that looks like to keep people accountable. When you can actually reference your culture and values is when you know you&amp;rsquo;re doing something right.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve also found that the more specific my values are, the easier hiring becomes. I don&amp;rsquo;t need to guess if this person will fit the culture because I can ask about their values and see if we align. If you&amp;rsquo;re rejecting candidates based on &amp;ldquo;culture fit&amp;rdquo;, but can&amp;rsquo;t point to your values, I&amp;rsquo;d reevaluate your process.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="example">Example&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The best example I&amp;rsquo;ve seen is &lt;a href="https://about.gitlab.com/handbook/values/">Gitlab&lt;/a>. And I know, they have &amp;ldquo;Collaboration&amp;rdquo; as a value.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>